Guide to the Yates Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Yates family papers
1678-1923
1714-1868
MS 568
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(7 boxes)
Principals in this collection are the Yates family of Schenectady, New York, the Delancy family and James Duane (1733-1797) and his descendants. The major part of the papers is made up of financial and legal papers relating to land transactions in New York state between the 1760s and the 1820s. Included are leases, rent receipts, boundary agreements, survey field books, account books and charts. Most of the correspondence consists of letters from Yates family members to their land agent, Charles Fuller. Of these, approximately fifty were written by Ann Elizabeth Delancy Yates, widow of Joseph Christopher Yates, governor of New York state. Other correspondents are James Duane and his descendants and members of the Delancy family.
Yates family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yates Family Papers were purchased in 1968 from the Winterthur Museum, which had acquired them from the estate of Helen Delancy Watkins of Schenectady, N.Y.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Yates Family Papers consist of 2.5 inches of correspondence, and 30 inches of legal and financial papers and descriptions of land holdings of the Yates family of Schenectady and other New York families. Most of the collection has to do with land. There are a few copies of seventeenth-century documents, but the concentration of legal and financial papers falls between the 1760s and the 1820s. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters from Yates family members to the land agent Charles Fuller (fl. 1845–1869) and others concerning land holdings and transactions and the collection of rents. Approximately fifty of the letters are from Ann Elizabeth (Delancy) Yates, widow of the New York State Governor Joseph Christopher Yates (1768–1837), written during the 1840s and 1850s. Other persons represented include Christopher Yates and his descendents from mid-eighteenth century to mid-nineteenth century, and James Duane (1733–1797) and his descendants, and members of the Delancy family.
Biographical / Historical
James Duane: jurist, mayor; admitted to N.Y. bar, 1754; member of Committee of Correspondence, 1774; delegate, Continental Congress, 1774-1784; member, N.Y. Provincial Convention, 1775, 1776, 1777; helped draft Articles of Confederation; advocated ratification of U.S. Constitution; first mayor of N.Y.C., 1784; member, N.Y. Senate, 1782-1785, 1789-1790; first U.S. judge, district of N.Y., 1789-1794.
Families; New York (State) -- History; Schenectady (N.Y.) -- History; Account books; Deeds; Duane, James, 1733-1797; Fuller, Charles, fl. 1845-1869; Yates, Ann Elizabeth Delancy; Yates, Christopher, 1947-; Yates, Joseph Christopher, 1768-1837; Delancey family; Yates family
- Inventory, 1678-1923
  - Correspondence
    - Yates family
      - Christopher Yates, 1767-1796 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
      - _____ Yates, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Richard August Yates, 1807
      - Ann Elizabeth (Delancy) Yates, 1843-1863 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 6)
      - _____ Yates, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Stephen Yates, 1847
    - Others
      - James Duane, 1762-1815 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Will Cockburn, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - William Seeber, 1774
      - John Delancy, 1839
      - John Delancy Watkins, 1846-1868 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - James C. Yates Paige, 1850-1856
      - Charles Fuller, 1846-1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Delancey W. Watkins, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Unidentified, 1842, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Legal and financial papers
    - 1678-1764 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 32)
    - 1765-1771 March (Box 3, Folder 33 - 40)
    - 1771 June-1772 (Box 4, Folder 41 - 44)
    - 1773-1780 (Box 5, Folder 45 - 55)
    - 1781-1810 (Box 6, Folder 56 - 68)
    - 1811-1924, undated (Box 7, Folder 69 - 79)
  - Maps, charts, and field books
    - 1735-1787, undated (Box 7, Folder 80 - 87)